Part 4.
You will hear part of an environmental science lecture
about a large bird called the dodo, which is now extinct.
First, you have some time to look at questions 31 to 40.
Question 1.
What are the most common diseases that birds can get?
The answer is the common cold and the common cold.
Question 2.
What is the most common disease that birds can get?
The answer is the common cold and the common cold.
Question 3.
What is the most common disease that birds can get?
Now listen carefully and answer questions 31 to 40.
One of the most famous cases of extinction is that of a bird known as the dodo.
In fact, there's even a saying in English,
as dead as the dodo, used to refer to something which no longer exists.
But for many centuries, the dodo was alive and well,
although it could only be found in one place,
the island of Mauritius in the Indian Ocean.
It was a very large bird, about one metre tall,
and over the centuries it had lost the ability to fly,
but it survived happily under the trees that covered the island.
Then, in the year 1507, the first Portuguese ships stopped at the island.
The sailors were carrying spices back to Europe
and found the island a convenient stopping place
where they could stock up with food and water for the rest of the voyage,
but they didn't settle on Mauritius.
However, in 1638, the Dutch arrived and set up a colony there.
These first human inhabitants of the island
found the dodo birds a convenient source of meat,
although not everyone liked the taste.
It's hard to get an accurate description of what the dodo actually looked like.
We do have some written records from sailors and a few pictures,
but we don't know how reliable these are.
The best-known picture is a Dutch painting
in which the bird appears to be extremely fat,
but this may not be accurate.
An Indian painting done at the same time shows a much thinner bird.
Although attempts were made to preserve the bodies of some of the birds,
no complete specimen survives.
In the early 17th century, four dried parts of a bird were known to exist.
Of these, three have disappeared,
so only one example of soft tissue from the dodo survives, a dodo head.
Bones have also been found,
but there's only one complete skeleton in existence.
This single dodo skeleton has recently been the subject of scientific research,
which suggests that many of the earlier beliefs about dodos may have been incorrect.
For example, early accounts of the birds mention how slow and clumsy it was,
but scientists now believe the bird's strong knee joints
would have made it capable of movement which was not slow, but actually quite fast.
In fact, one 17th century sailor wrote that he found the birds hard to catch.
It's true that the dodo's small wings wouldn't have allowed it to leave the ground,
but the scientists suggest that these were probably employed for balance
while going over uneven ground.
Another group of scientists carried out analysis of the dodo's skull.
They found that the reports of the lack of intelligence of the dodo
were not borne out by their research,
which suggested the bird's brain was not small, but average in size.
In fact, in relation to its body size, it was similar to that of the pigeon,
which is known to be a highly intelligent bird.
The researchers also found that the structure of the bird's skull
suggested that one sense which was particularly well developed was that of smell,
so the dodo may also have been particularly good at locating ripe fruit
and other food in the island's thick vegetation.
So it looks as if the dodo was better able to survive and defend itself
than was originally believed.
Yet, less than 200 years after Europeans first arrived on the island,
they had become extinct.
So what was the reason for this?
For a long time it was believed that the dodo's were hunted to extinction,
but scientists now believe the situation was more complicated than this.
Another factor may have been the new species brought to the island by the sailors.
These included dogs, which would have been a threat to the dodos,
and also monkeys, which ate the fruit that was the main part of the dodo's diet.
These were brought to the island deliberately,
but the ships also brought another type of creature, rats,
which came to land from the ships and rapidly overran the island.
These upset the ecology of the island, not just the dodos, but other species too.
However, they were a particular danger to the dodos because they consumed their eggs,
and since each dodo only laid one at a time,
this probably had a devastating effect on populations.
However, we now think that probably the main cause of the bird's extinction
was not the introduction of non-native species, but the introduction of agriculture.
This meant that the forest that had once covered all the island,
and that had provided a perfect home for the dodo,
was cut down so that crops such as sugar could be grown.
So, although the dodo had survived for thousands of years, suddenly it was gone.
Thank you for watching!
This is the end of the listening test.
In the IELTS test, you would now have 10 minutes to transfer your answers to the answer sheet.